Environmental Studies Program; Records ua696.003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Environmental Studies Program Records1969-1976
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany. Environmental Studies Program
ua696.003
1.33 cubic ft.
A multidisciplinary program active from 1970-1977 that encouraged the study and research of environmental issues.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Administrative History
The Environmental Studies Program of the State University of New York at Albany (as the University at Albany, SUNY was then known) was established in 1970 under President Louis T. Benezet. Its inception came at a time of increasing interest in environmental issues through programs such as the Environmental Forum, a community open forum that brought together academic and local activists and was organized by Louis Ismay since 1969 at the university. The Environmental Decisions Commission was also created under President Benezet in 1971. It was responsible for considering and advising on environmental issues on campus. At the same time, publication began of an environmental student newsletter, Environmental Issues.
The Environmental Studies Program was organized by a Program Planning Committee coordinated by Eugene McLaren, a professor of chemistry and a researcher in the Atmospheric Science Research Center (ASRC). An Advisory Committee headed by Vincent Schaefer, Director of the ASRC, aided the planning committee. The Environmental Studies Program was designed to be multi-disciplinary and pull together faculty like Louis (Lou) Ismay, Rosemary Nichols, and Robert Rienow. The resulting program began in 1972 by designating existing courses as environmentally related and offering several new classes in existing departments. The official environmental major or second field was established in 1973.
In 1975, after having been officially in operation for two years, the program had a total of 60 students in the major or as dual-majors. A Presidents Select Committee found the program too fragmented and diffuse and recommended that it be terminated. A Task Force considered the issue in 1976 and concurred, noting that budget constraints at the time prevented the program from being properly expanded and developed. Despite appeals to new President Emmett Fields from student and faculty groups, the program was dissolved in 1977.
Scope and Contents
The students, faculty, and administrative committees of the Environmental Studies Program generated the materials in this collection during its five years of existence. Numerous members of the program, most notably Lou Ismay, Eugene McLaren, and Rosemary Nichols, collected these materials. The records consist of memoranda, correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, and class materials. There is little material from the years that the program was in full operation. Instead, most of the documents concentrate on the programs creation (1970-1971). The materials that do represent the years of operation generally consist of class materials or course descriptions rather than administrative materials.
Also included are materials generated by offshoots and side projects of the program, like the Capital District Solid Waste Environmental Education Program (CD SWEEP) and the student newsletter, Environmental Issues. The largest of these projects is the Albany Peoples Pipewatch
Related Collections iare the papers of Jackson Davis, Louis Ismay, Vincent Schaefer, Eugene McLaren, and Robert Rienow, all of whom were involved in the program and the records of the Environmental Decisions Commission, Office of the President, and the University Senate.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into three series arranged chronologically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to student material in Series 2 is restricted, please consult an archivist to view this material.
Conservation and the Environment; Environmental education; Environmental education--Activity programs--United States; Web Archives; State University of New York at Albany; Ismay, Louis F.; McLaren, Eugene; Nichols, Rosemary
- Administrative Files, 1969-1976; 1; 0.66 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials directly related to the creation, operation, and termination of the Environmental Studies Program. Best represented are the early years during the creation phase, when several committees were planning the program. These include the President's Advisory Committee and the Program Planning Committee that operated in 1970-1971. These were later replaced by the Steering Committee and the Environmental Studies Committee.
  Most of the materials in this series are memoranda that represent communications between committee members as well as between committee members and university administration. There are also meeting minutes, reports, correspondence and class materials. For an overview of the programs creation, see Box 2, Folder 8, Report on Environmental Studies Program, which is composed of materials organized by Paul Bulger and Lou Ismay.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Pine Bush Alternative Plan, 1973-1976; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - American Society for Public Administration, "The Environmental Crisis" Conference, Conference Materials, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Articles, News Clippings, 1969-1973; 1975; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Capital District Solid Waste Environmental Education Program (CD SWEEP), 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Class Materials, 1974-1975; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Committee to Report on Attitudes and Values on Environment of Students (C.R.A.V.E.S.), Survey, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971; 1975-1976; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Course Listings and Descriptions, 1970-1972; 1975; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Environmental Decisions Commission, 1970; 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Environmental Issues, Newsletter, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Environmental Program Steering Committee, Meeting Agendas, Minutes, Memoranda, Reports, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Environmental Studies Advisory Committee, Meeting Minutes, Memoranda, Reports, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Environmental Studies Program, Draft Proposal, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Fliers, Leaflets, 1970; 1976; undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Grant Proposals, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Grant Sources, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Interim Director Search Committee, Memoranda, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - "Man and Environment," Program Proposal, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Memoranda, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - New York State Food Conference, Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - "Report of the Subcommittee on Biology in Public Affairs", 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Report on Environmental Studies Program, Paul Bulger and Lou Ismay, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1970, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Response to Recommendation to Terminate Program, Memorandum, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Smog, Litter, Overpopulation, Pollution (SLOP) Program, Leaflets, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Social Ecology Program Proposal, undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Student Committee for Environmental Studies, Recommendations, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - "The SUNY-A Environmental Studies Proposal Including Project Research in the Five Rivers Area," Environmental Studies Advisory Committee, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - "The Universities and Environmental Quality: Commitment to Problem Focused Education," US Office of Science and Technology, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
- Writings, 1970-1976; 2; 0.33 cubic ft.
  - Atmospheric Sciences Research Center, "Small Utility Internal Combustion Engine Test", 1972 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 1)
  - Student, "Electric Power Generation and Environmental Prospect", 1970 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 2)
  - Student, "The Environment of a College: A Study of the Campus and Construction of the State University of New York at Albany", 1975 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 3)
  - Fonseca, John, "Law and Society" Part I, Notes, 1972 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 4)
  - Fonseca, John, "Law and Society" Part II, 1972 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 5)
  - Student, "SUNY-A Recycle: An Institutionalized Non-volunteer Paper Recycling Program", 1974 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 6)
  - Student, Internship Journal, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 7)
  - McLaren, Eugene, "Toward a New Town in Greene County", undated (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 8)
  - Moore, John, "Man and his Environment: A Syllabus", 1971 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 9)
  - Nichols, Rosemary, "Environmental Law: Cases and Commentary", 1975 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 10)
  - Nichols, Rosemary, "The Present Condition of Aesthetic Zoning: Has Beauty Found Shelter?", undated (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 11)
  - Northeastern Regional Organization, National Speleological Society, "Report on New York State Cave Survey Information", 1974 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 12)
  - Student, "An Undergraduate Research Study of Chemical Pollution in the Campus Pond", 1972 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 13)
  - Werking, James, Motorcycle Safety: Introductory Curriculum", 1975 (Box 1 (2-Writings), Folder 14)
- Albany People's Pipewatch, 1970-1976; 3; 0.33 cubic ft.
  An offshoot of John Cronin's People Pipewatch, Albany Peoples Pipewatch was housed in the Department of Fine Arts of the State University of New York at Albany. Its volunteers monitored discharge pipes leading to the Hudson River and compared the resulting effluents to the allowable limits in the National Pollution Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permits. This series contains mostly NPDES Notices and drafts of the permits and are indexed by the company owning the discharge pipe.
  - Airco Industrial Gases, Profile, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 1)
  - Albany County Jail, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 2)
  - Allegheny Ludlum Steel Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 3)
  - Allied Chemical Corporation, NPDES Notice, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 4)
  - American Oil Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 5)
  - Atlantic Cement Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 6)
  - Bendix Corporation, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 7)
  - Callanan Industries, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 8)
  - City of Mechanicville, NPDES Notice, Notes, Profile, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 9)
  - City of Watervliet, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 10)
  - Completed Sample Forms, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Citizens Protecting the Environment, List of Complaints Received, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, EPA, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 13)
  - Ford Motor Company, NPDES Notice, Profile, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 14)
  - General Electric, Fort Edward, NPDES Notice, Profile, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 15)
  - Hercules Incorporated, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 16)
  - HP Hood and Sons Inc., NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 17)
  - Hudson Cement Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 18)
  - International Playtex Corporation, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 19)
  - Metropolitan Petroleum Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 20)
  - Mobil Oil Corporation, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 21)
  - Niagra Mohawk Power Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 22)
  - Normanskill, Sample Form, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 23)
  - New York State Department of Health, Griffin Lab, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 24)
  - New York State Environmental Facilities Corporation, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 25)
  - New York State Thruway Authority, NPDES Notice, Notes, Sample Form, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 26)
  - Pepsi Cola, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 27)
  - Shell Oil Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 28)
  - Sun Oil Company, NPDES Notice, Notes, undated (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 29)
  - Texaco Incorporated, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 30)
  - Tobin Packing Company, 1970-1971, undated (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 31)
  - Town of Bethlehem, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 32)
  - Town of Colonie, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 33)
  - Town of East Greenbush, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 34)
  - Town of Guilderland, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 35)
  - Town of Ulster, Profile, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 36)
  - US Steel Corporation, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 37)
  - Village of Altamont, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 38)
  - Village of Green Island, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 39)
  - Village of South Glens Falls, NPDES Notice, Notes, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Albany People's Pipewatch), Folder 40)
- Web Archives, 2006 September 15-2016 September 18; 4; 278 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - http://www.albany.edu/undergraduate_bulletin/program_environmental_science.html - University Archives collection, 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albany.edu/undergraduate_bulletin/program_environmental_science.html, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Warc 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albany.edu/undergraduate_bulletin/program_environmental_science.html - Internet Archive collection, 2006 September 15-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 2)